RG 005:031, Office of the Governor: Chester Bowles (1949-1951)
Connecticut State Library
Chester Bowles records
1949-1951
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Governor (1949-1951: Bowles)
5 cubic feet
Gov. Chester Bowles' subject files.
RG005_031
T001275
Biographical Note
Born: April 5, 1901, Springfield, Massachusetts.
College: Yale, 1924.
Political Party: Democrat.
Offices: Governor of Connecticut, 1949-1951; U.S. Ambassador to India, 1951-1953 & 1963-1969; U.S. Congress, 1959-1961; U.S. State Dept., 1961-1963.
Died: May 25, 1986, Essex, Connecticut.
Thought to be one of Connecticut's most liberal governors, Chester Bowles was the last governor of the state to serve a two-year term. Bowles credited his liberalism to the influence of certain members of his family, his desire to be in public service, and what he saw government accomplish during the Great Depression and World War II. When he graduated from Yale in 1924, he went to work for a New York City advertising agency and by 1929, he and William Benton opened their own advertising company. Despite the economic difficulties of the 1930's, Benton and Bowles made enormous profits so that by the 1940's both men were able to leave their company to pursue other interests. For Bowles, this took the form of government service. Bowles was married twice. His fist wife was Julia Fisk. They had two children before their divorce in 1932. Shortly after this, he married Dorothy Stebbin and they had three children.
When Connecticut developed programs as part of World War II, Governor Hurley appointed Bowles to oversee the rationing of products in the state. In 1943, Bowles took a similar position with the Federal Government's Office of Policy and Management Council. Turned on to what he saw government capable of doing during the depression and the war, Bowles was convinced government could also overcome poverty and injustice in society. He decided that the best place to begin this work was on the state level and in 1946 he sought the support of Connecticut's Democratic leaders to be that party's candidate for governor. However, he was unaware of the existence of John Bailey during his visit to Hartford and Bailey used this slight to back Wilbert Snow for governor. Snow won the nomination over Bowles and Bailey won the position of state party chairman, which he held for 29 years. Bowles again ran for the Democratic nomination for governor in 1948, only this time he sought Bailey's support. Nominated by his party, a private poll gave him no chance of winning the November election. Nevertheless, Bowls was able to overcome these odds and was elected governor for the next two years.
The 1949 legislative session was not a smooth one for Bowles. He produced a budget that was balanced, but only because he introduced the concept of bonding funds to pay for the projects that he advocated. The Republican controlled General Assembly produced its own budget. Bowles also proposed replacing the sales tax with an income tax, but this idea quickly died in the legislature. When the assembly failed to agree on a budget by its mandated time for adjournment, Bowles had to call it back into special session to complete this task before the new fiscal year began on July 1, 1949. He would eventually call four more special sessions to deal with his concerns for improving Connecticut and its government. He was successful in getting legislation passed so that more housing could be built in the state. He also had some civil rights legislation passed, made some improvements in welfare benefits, provided for more buildings at the state's colleges and university, and instituted more teacher training. However, many of his progressive ideas for government and society were unacceptable during his term, although most were passed under later governors.
Bowles ran for reelection in 1950 and lost to John Lodge. Democrats close to him conceded that he had tried to do too much too soon. Bowles remained active in government, serving in Congress and with the administration of President Kennedy. He was also ambassador to India for a number of years. A prolific writer, Bowles died in 1986 at the age of 85. His house in Essex, overlooking the Connecticut River, was offered for sale in 1991 at a value of nearly three million dollars. In 1972, he donated large sections of his property along the river to be used as a wildlife refuge. Connecticut's Route 9, which runs through Middletown, is named in his honor.
Bibliography
Bowles, Chester. Promises to Keep: My Years in Public Life, 1941-1969.New York: Harper's, 1971.
_______________. Tomorrow Without Fear. New Haven, 1946.
Congressional Quarterly's Guide to United States Elections. Washington, D.C.: Congressional Quarterly, 1994 [CSL call number GIS Ref JK 1967 .C662 1994.
Glashan, Roy R. American Governors and Gubernatorial Elections, 1775-1975. Stillwater, Minn.: Croixside Press, 1975 [CSL call number JK 2447 .G53 1975].
Lieberman, Joseph I. The Legacy: Connecticut Politics, 1930-1980. Hartford, Conn.: Spoonwood Press, c1981 [CSL call number JK 3395 .L3 1981].
Sobel, Robert and John Raimo. Biographical Directory of the Governors of the United States, 1789-1978. Westport, Conn.: Meckler Books, 1978 [CSL call number GIS Ref E 176 .B573].
Van Dusen, Albert E. Connecticut. New York: Random House, 1961 [CSL call number HistRef F 94 .V3].
Scope and Content
Gov. Chester Bowles' subject files related to state agencies, commissions, legislative bills, and appointments among other topics.
Arrangement
Series 1. Subject Files.
Related Material
located in Manuscripts and Archives, Sterling Memorial Library, Yale University. These papers include correspondence, speeches, and photographs from Bowles' time as Governor.
Index Terms
Persons:
Bowles, Chester, 1901-
Subjects:
Bowles, Chester, 1901- -- Archives; Connecticut. Office of the Governor -- Archives; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950 -- Sources; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1951- -- Sources; Governors -- Connecticut -- Archives
Document Types:
Records
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Subject Files
  - Advisory Personnel Committee (Box 528)
  - Aeronautics, Dept. of (Box 528)
  - Agricultural Experiment Station (Box 528)
  - American School for the Deaf (Box 528)
  - Attorney General (Box 528)
  - Auditors of Public Accounts (Box 528)
  - Banking Commission (Box 528)
  - Budget Division (Box 528)
  - Care and treatment of the Chronically Ill, Aged & Infirm, Commission on (Box 528)
  - Child Study Home (Box 528)
  - Civil Defense (Box 528)
  - Conn. National Guard (Box 528)
  - Connecticut State Hospital (Box 528)
  - Connecticut State Prison (Box 528)
  - Construction – Real Assets Reports (Box 528)
  - Dental Commission (Box 528)
  - Development Commission (Box 528)
  - Education, Board of (Box 528)
  - Employment, Full (Committee on) (Box 528)
  - Employment of the Physically Handicapped (Box 528)
  - Extradition (Box 528)
  - Fairfield State Hospital (Box 528)
  - Finance Advisory committee (Box 528)
  - Finance and Control, Department of (Box 528)
  - Fine Arts, Commission on (Box 528)
  - Fisheries & Game, Board of (Box 528)
  - Fitch Property – Vet’s Home & Hospital (Box 528)
  - Flood Control and Water Policy Com[mission] (Box 528)
  - Flood Control Compact – Legislation in Connecticut, Amendments (Box 528)
  - Flood Control – Mansfield Hollow Resources (Box 528)
  - Forest & Wildlife, Commission on (Box 528)
  - Food and Drugs Commission (Box 528)
  - Gaylord Farms Sanatorium (Box 529)
  - Governor’s Conference on Children and Youth (Box 529)
  - Groton – New London Bridge Commission (Box 529)
  - Harmon Exhibit (Box 529)
  - Hartford Bridge Commission (Box 529)
  - Hadlyme Ferry (Box 529)
  - Health Committee (Box 529)
  - Health Department (Box 529)
  - Highway Department (Box 529)
  - Highway Safety Commission (Box 529)
  - Highways – Darien Bypass (Box 529)
  - Highways – Expressway E – W Hartford (Box 529)
  - Highways – Miscellaneous (Box 529)
  - Highways – Miscellaneous [folder 2] (Box 529)
    - Statement of Purpose of Highway Construction Projects, 1949-1950 (Box 529)
    - Statement of Purpose of Highway Construction Projects, 1950 July1-December 31 (Box 529)
    - Statement of Purpose of Highway Construction Projects, Fiscal year 1949-1950 (Box 529)
    - [Statement of Purpose of] Relocation Route U.S. 1 Darien (Box 529)
    - [Statement of Purpose of] East – West Expressway Hartford, Broad St. to Sisson Avenue (Box 529)
    - [Statement of Purpose of] East – West Expressway Trout Brook to School House Corner West Hartford and Farmington (Box 529)
    - [Statement of Purpose of] Wilbur Cross Highway – Union Route 20 to Mass. State Line (Box 529)
    - Proposed Reconstruction of U.S. 1 New Haven Harborfront, 1947 May (Box 529)
    - Statement of Purpose Additional Highway Construction, Project Fiscal Year 1949-1950 (Box 529)
    - Wilbur Cross Parkway Tolls (Box 529)
    - [Statement of] Proposed Highway Improvement Bolton Notch, Bolton, Connecticut (Box 529)
  - Highways – Relocation Route 1 New Haven (Box 529)
  - Housing (Box 529)
  - Housing – Home Ownership (Box 529)
  - Housing Authority, Conn. State (Box 529)
  - Housing Authority, Conn. State, 8 folders (Box 530)
  - Housing Progress, 1950 April 14 (Box 530)
  - Humane and Welfare Institutions Building Program Commission (Box 531)
  - Insurance Commission (Box 531)
  - Intergovernmental Cooperation Comm[ission] (Box 531)
  - Inter – Racial Commission (Box 531)
  - Interstate Sanitation Commission (Box 531)
  - Investment Committee (Box 531)
  - Israel Putnam Memorial Camp Commission (Box 531)
  - Labor and Factory Inspection, Dept. of (Box 531)
  - Legislative Council (Box 531)
  - Liquor Control Commission (Box 531)
  - Long Lane School (Box 531)
  - Mansfield State Hospital (Box 531)
  - Marketing Authority, Conn[ecticut] (Box 531)
  - Merritt Parkway Commission (Box 531)
  - Military Dept. (Box 531)
  - Motor Vehicles Dept. (Box 531)
  - Mystic Oral School (Box 531)
  - Natural Gas (Box 531)
  - New Britain General Hospital (Box 531)
  - New England Interstate Water Pollution Control Commission (Box 531)
  - Norwich State Hospital (Box 531)
  - Old Lyme – Old Saybrook Bridge Comm[ission] (Box 531)
  - Opticians, Commission of (Box 531)
  - Park & Forest Commission (Box 531)
  - Personnel Department (Box 531)
  - Plant Tenancy -- Chance Vought (Box 531)
  - Plant Tenancy -- Southington (Box 531)
  - Police Department (Box 531)
  - Public Expenditure Council, Conn. (Box 531)
  - Public Health Council (Box 531)
  - Public School Building Commission (Box 531)
  - Public Utilities Commission (Box 532)
  - Public Welfare Council (Box 532)
  - Purchasing Department (Box 532)
  - Saving Bank Railroad Investment Committee (Box 532)
  - Savings Banks Life Insurance Fund (Box 532)
  - Seaside Sanatorium (Box 532)
  - Southbury Training School (Box 532)
  - State Government Organization Comm. (Box 532)
  - State Mental Hospitals, Joint Committee of the (Box 532)
  - State Police (Box 532)
  - State Training Schools, Joint Committee of the (Box 532)
  - Steamship Terminals, Commission of (Box 532)
  - Steel Advisory Committee (Box 532)
  - Tax Department (Box 532)
  - Treasurer’s Office (Box 532)
  - Tuberculosis Commission (Box 532)
  - Unemployment Compensation (Box 532)
  - Unemployment Compensation Committee (Box 532)
  - University of Connecticut (Box 532)
  - Veterans Home & Hospital (Box 532)
  - Water Commission (Box 532)
  - Welfare Department (Box 532)